{
  "2005": [
    {
      "question": "The presence of a pallial sinus in a bivalve shell indicates its:",
      "options": [
          "infaunal habitat",
          "epifaunal habitat",
          "planktonic habitat",
          "pelagic habitat"
      ],
      "answer": "infaunal habitat"
    },
    {
      "question": "Character of sutures is the sole criterion for recognizing the evolution of ammonoids during the:",
      "options": [
          "Early Paleozoic Periods",
          "Late Paleozoic Periods",
          "Mesozoic Era",
          "Cenozoic Era"
      ],
      "answer": "Mesozoic Era"
    },
    {
      "question": "As index fossils, brachiopods were important during the:",
      "options": [
          "Late Cretaceous",
          "Middle Jurassic",
          "Early Jurassic",
          "Late Paleozoic"
      ],
      "answer": "Late Paleozoic"
    }
  ],
  "2006": [
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following groups of organisms belongs to terrestrial / fresh-water environment?",
      "options": [
          "Echinoids",
          "Brachiopods",
          "Corals",
          "Pulmonate gastropods"
      ],
      "answer": "Pulmonate gastropods"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the following: Group I: P. Micraster Q. Phacops R. Equus S. Barappasaurus Group II: 1. Trilobite 2. Dinosaur 3. Mammal 4. Echinoid",
      "options": [
          "P-1, Q-2, R-3, S-4",
          "P-2, Q-1, R-4, S-3",
          "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1",
          "P-4, Q-1, R-3, S-2"
      ],
      "answer": "P-4, Q-1, R-3, S-2"
    },
    {
        "question": "Acme zone indicates the:",
        "options": [
            "range of a fossil species",
            "absence of a fossil species",
            "maximum abundance of a fossil species",
            "migration of a fossil species"
        ],
        "answer": "maximum abundance of a fossil species"
    }
  ],
  "2007": [
    {
      "question": "The occurrence of ammonites in a sequence suggests:",
      "options": [
          "Cenozoic age and freshwater environment",
          "Cenozoic age and marine environment",
          "Mesozoic age and freshwater environment",
          "Mesozoic age and marine environment"
      ],
      "answer": "Mesozoic age and marine environment"
    },
    {
        "question": "The presence of reef corals in a sedimentary sequence indicates that deposition took place:",
        "options": [
            "near the equator",
            "near the poles",
            "in fluvial environment",
            "in deep sea environment"
        ],
        "answer": "near the equator"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the organisms listed in Group I with their respective symmetry elements in Group II: Group I: P. Brachiopods Q. Pelecypods R. Echinoids S. Helically coiled gastropods Group II: 1. Asymmetric 2. Plane of symmetry bisects the two valves 3. Plane of symmetry lies between the two valves 4. Five-fold radial symmetry",
      "options": [
          "P-1, Q-2, R-3, S-4",
          "P-4, Q-1, R-2, S-3",
          "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1",
          "P-2, Q-3, R-4, S-1"
      ],
      "answer": "P-2, Q-3, R-4, S-1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the fossil taxa listed in Group I with their characteristic morphological features in Group II:\n\nGroup I:\nP. Paradoxides\nQ. Didymograptus\nR. Physa\nS. Ceratites\n\nGroup II:\n1. Two pendent stipes\n2. Sinistral coiling\n3. Genal spines\n4. Sutures with undivided saddles",
      "options": [
          "P-3, Q-2, R-4, S-1",
          "P-3, Q-1, R-2, S-4",
          "P-2, Q-1, R-4, S-3",
          "P-2, Q-1, R-3, S-4"
      ],
      "answer": "P-3, Q-1, R-2, S-4"
    }
  ],
  "2008": [
    {
      "question": "Globotruncana-bearing sequence indicates a shallow marine sedimentary succession deposited during:",
      "options": [
          "Cretaceous",
          "Eocene",
          "Jurassic",
          "Oligocene"
      ],
      "answer": "Cretaceous"
    },
    {
        "question": "Terebratula is the characteristic genera of:",
        "options": [
            "Mesozoic",
            "Cenozoic",
            "Quaternary",
            "Paleozoic"
        ],
        "answer": "No option is correct"
    }
  ],
  "2009": [
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following is a Lower Gondwana flora?",
      "options": [
          "Gangamopteris",
          "Ptilophyllum",
          "Otozamites",
          "Nilssonia"
      ],
      "answer": "Gangamopteris"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a Middle Cambrian Trilobite?",
      "options": [
          "Olenus",
          "Paradoxides",
          "Olenellus",
          "Phacops"
      ],
      "answer": "Paradoxides"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a pelecypod shell, if umbos curve is in such a way that the beak points in an anterior direction, the umbos are:",
      "options": [
          "Opisthogyrate",
          "Prosogyrate",
          "Orthogyrate",
          "Spirogyrate"
      ],
      "answer": "Prosogyrate"
    }
  ],
  "2010": [
    {
      "question": "Match the dentition type in Group I with the Bivalvia genus in Group II.\nGroup I: (P) Heterodont, (Q) Desmodont, (R) Dysodont, (S) Schizodont\nGroup II: (1) Trigonia, (2) Cerastoderma, (3) Mya, (4) Mytilus",
      "options": [
          "(P) - 2, (Q) - 3, (R) - 1, (S) - 4",
          "(P) - 1, (Q) - 3, (R) - 2, (S) - 4",
          "(P) - 2, (Q) - 3, (R) - 4, (S) - 1",
          "(P) - 1, (Q) - 2, (R) - 3, (S) - 4"
      ],
      "answer": "(P) - 2, (Q) - 3, (R) - 4, (S) - 1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following flora belongs to the Lower Gondwana?",
        "options": [
            "Gangamopteris",
            "Cladophebis",
            "Sphenopteris",
            "Ptilophyllum"
        ],
        "answer": "Gangamopteris"
    }
  ],
  "2011": [
    {
      "question": "Match the feature in Group I with appropriate taxon in Group II:\n\nGroup-I:\nP. Monomyarian\nQ. Deltidial plates\nR. Corona\nS. Epitheca\n\nGroup-II:\n1. Echinoidea\n2. Anthozoa\n3. Pelecypoda\n4. Brachiopoda",
      "options": [
          "P-3, Q-4, R-1, S-2",
          "P-4, Q-2, R-1, S-3",
          "P-4, Q-3, R-2, S-1",
          "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1"
      ],
      "answer": "P-3, Q-4, R-1, S-2"
    }
  ],
  "2012": [
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following fossils is found in rocks of Cambrian age?",
      "options": [
          "Redlichia",
          "Fenestella",
          "Syringothyris",
          "Otoceras"
      ],
      "answer": "Redlichia"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the morphological features described in Group I with their names listed in Group II: Group-I: P. Masticatory apparatus in Echinoidea Q. Triangular cavity near umbo of Brachiopoda R. Calcareous secretions in siphuncle of Cephalopoda S. Genital plate in Echinoidea Group-II: 1. Cameral deposits 2. Madreporite 3. Deltihyrum 4. Aristotle's lantern",
      "options": [
          "P-3, Q-4, R-1, S-2",
          "P-4, Q-3, R-1, S-2",
          "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1",
          "P-4, Q-2, R-3, S-1"
      ],
      "answer": "P-4, Q-3, R-1, S-2"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following flora represents Upper Gondwana?",
      "options": [
          "Noeggerathiopsis",
          "Gangamopteris",
          "Dicroidium",
          "Vertebraria"
      ],
      "answer": "Dicroidium"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following is a Primate fossil?",
      "options": [
          "Hipparion",
          "Ramapithecus",
          "Equus",
          "Stegolophodon"
      ],
      "answer": "Ramapithecus"
    }
  ],
  "2013": [
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following morphological features is ABSENT in the Class Pelecypoda?",
      "options": [
          "Umbo",
          "Deltidium",
          "Pallial sinus",
          "Resilifier"
      ],
      "answer": "Deltidium"
    }
  ],
  "2014": [
    {
      "question": "Match the genera in Group-I with the phyla in Group-II: Group-I: P. Mya Q. Micraster R. Olenoides S. Leptaena Group-II: 1. Echinodermata 2. Mollusca 3. Brachiopoda 4. Arthropoda",
      "options": [
          "P-3, Q-4, R-1, S-2",
          "P-2, Q-1, R-3, S-4",
          "P-2, Q-4, R-1, S-3",
          "P-2, Q-1, R-4, S-3"
      ],
      "answer": "P-2, Q-1, R-4, S-3"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following flora is a conifer?",
      "options": [
          "Glossopteris",
          "Gangamopteris",
          "Buriadia",
          "Schizoneura"
      ],
      "answer": "Buriadia"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following belongs to the Equidae family?",
        "options": [
            "Stegodon",
            "Stegolophodon",
            "Ramapithecus",
            "Gigantopithecus"
        ],
        "answer": "None of the options belong to Equidae"
    }
  ],
  "2015": [
    {
      "question": "Which of the following group of fossils became extinct at the Permo-Triassic boundary?",
      "options": [
          "Graptolite",
          "Trilobite",
          "Ammonite",
          "Ediacaran"
      ],
      "answer": "Trilobite"
    },
    {
        "question": "Match the Lamellibranchia genera in Group-I with their dentition pattern in Group-II.\nGroup-I: (i) Glycimeris, (ii) Trigonia, (iii) Lucina, (iv) Mytilus\nGroup-II: (P) Schizodont, (Q) Taxodont, (R) Dysodont, (S) Heterodont",
        "options": [
            "(i) - Q, (ii) - P, (iii) - S, (iv) - R",
            "(i) - P, (ii) - Q, (iii) - R, (iv) - S",
            "(i) - Q, (ii) - P, (iii) - R, (iv) - S",
            "(i) - S, (ii) - R, (iii) - Q, (iv) - P"
        ],
        "answer": "(i) - Q, (ii) - P, (iii) - R, (iv) - S"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following Brachiopod genera is considered as 'living fossil'?",
      "options": [
          "Lingula",
          "Productus",
          "Atrypa",
          "Spirifer"
      ],
      "answer": "Lingula"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following fossil genera is/are invertebrate? (Multiple Select Question)",
        "options": [
            "Megalodon",
            "Spondylus",
            "Stegodon",
            "Telemastodon"
        ],
        "answer": [ "Megalodon" , "Spondylus"]
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following trilobites have two to four thoracic segments and are eyeless? (Multiple Select Question)",
        "options": [
            "Agnostus",
            "Olenellus",
            "Calymene",
            "Microdiscus"
        ],
        "answer": ["Agnostus", "Microdiscus"]
    }
  ],
  "2016": [
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following is an upper Gondwana flora?",
      "options": [
          "Ptilophyllum",
          "Phyllotheca",
          "Glossopteris",
          "Schizoneura"
      ],
      "answer": "Ptilophyllum"
    },
    {
      "question": "Match features mentioned in Group I with the fossil types in Group II:\n\nGroup I:\ni. Escutcheon\nii. Plastron\niii. Delthyrium\niv. Siphuncle\n\nGroup II:\nP. Brachiopoda\nQ. Nautiloidea\nR. Echinoidea\nS. Bivalvia",
      "options": [
          "i-S, ii-R, iii-Q, iv-P",
          "i-S, ii-R, iii-P, iv-Q",
          "i-S, ii-P, iii-Q, iv-R",
          "i-R, ii-Q, iii-P, iv-S"
      ],
      "answer": "i-S, ii-R, iii-P, iv-Q"
  },
  {
      "question": "Choose the burrowing form(s) of bivalve. (Multiple Select Question)",
      "options": [
          "Mya",
          "Teredo",
          "Pecten",
          "Venus"
      ],
      "answer": ["Mya", "Venus"]
  }
  ],
  "2017": [
    {
      "question": "In which one of the following mass extinction periods trilobites became extinct?",
      "options": [
          "Devonian",
          "Permian",
          "Triassic",
          "Cretaceous"
      ],
      "answer": "Permian"
    },
    {
        "question": "Choose the correct combination(s) of type of dentition of Bivalvia and the corresponding representative genus. (Multiple Select Question)",
        "options": [
            "Taxodont-Nuculus",
            "Isodont-Spondylus",
            "Pachydont-Hippurites",
            "Desmodont-Mya"
        ],
        "answer": ["Taxodont-Nuculus","Isodont-Spondylus","Pachydont-Hippurites" , "Desmodont-Mya"]
    },
    {
      "question": "A hellically coiled ammonite Turrilites is differentiated from externally resembling Gastropoda Turritela by:",
      "options": [
          "apical angle",
          "number of whorls",
          "direction of coiling",
          "chambered shell"
      ],
      "answer": "chambered shell"
    },
    {
      "question": "The facial suture of trilobites running through the genal angle is known as:",
      "options": [
          "proparian",
          "marginal",
          "gonatoparian",
          "opisthoparian"
      ],
      "answer": "gonatoparian"
    },
    {
      "question": "The tubefeet in echinoids emerge through:",
      "options": [
          "interambulacral plates",
          "ambulacral plates",
          "bourrelets",
          "plastron"
      ],
      "answer": "ambulacral plates"
    }
  ],
  "2018": [
    {
      "question": "The type of dentition found in Trigonia is:",
      "options": [
          "schizodont",
          "taxodont",
          "pachydont",
          "isodont"
      ],
      "answer": "schizodont"
    },
    {
        "question": "The correct order of marine benthic habitats with increasing water depths is:",
        "options": [
            "abyssal, bathyal, neritic",
            "neritic, abyssal, bathyal",
            "neritic, bathyal, abyssal",
            "bathyal, abyssal, neritic"
        ],
        "answer": "neritic, bathyal, abyssal"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following invertebrates has the most primitive visual system?",
        "options": [
            "Ammonites",
            "Brachiopods",
            "Gastropods",
            "Trilobites"
        ],
        "answer": "Trilobites"
    },
    {
      "question": "Identify the correct morphological features corresponding to numbers I – IV in the echinoid illustrated below:",
      "options": [
          "I-Periproct, II-Ambulacra, III-Interambulacra, IV-Peristome",
          "I-Periproct, II-Interambulacra, III-Ambulacra, IV-Peristome",
          "I-Peristome, II-Interambulacra, III-Ambulacra, IV-Periproct",
          "I-Peristome, II-Ambulacra, III-Interambulacra, IV-Periproct"
      ],
      "answer": "I-Periproct, II-Ambulacra, III-Interambulacra, IV-Peristome"
    },
    {
        "question": "Match the morphological features/life processes in Group I with corresponding organisms in Group II: Group I: P. Water vascular system Q. Moulting R. Jet propulsion locomotion S. Lophophore Group II: 1. Cephalopoda 2. Echinodermata 3. Brachiopoda 4. Trilobita",
        "options": [
            "P-2, Q-3, R-1, S-4",
            "P-3, Q-4, R-2, S-1",
            "P-2, Q-4, R-1, S-3",
            "P-4, Q-3, R-2, S-1"
        ],
        "answer": "P-2, Q-4, R-1, S-3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Hermatypic corals are typically found in:\n(Multiple Select Question)",
        "options": [
            "the photic zone",
            "warm and clear water",
            "cool deep water",
            "reefs"
        ],
        "answer": ["the photic zone", "warm and clear water", "reefs"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Major mass extinction events occured in the (Multiple Select Question)",
      "options": [
          "end Silurian",
          "end Carboniferous",
          "end Permian",
          "eraly Deyonian"
      ],
      "answer": "end Permian"
    }
  ],
  "2019": [
    {
      "question": "Fossils of burrows and footprints are known as:",
      "options": [
          "pseudofossils",
          "coprolites",
          "body fossils",
          "trace fossils"
      ],
      "answer": "trace fossils"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is/are mode(s) of preservation of fossils? (Multiple Select Question)",
        "options": [
            "Small organisms get trapped on viscous resins secreted by trees",
            "Leaves preserved as thin films of carbon",
            "Negative impressions of hard parts of organisms",
            "Mineral growths that branch like ferns"
        ],
        "answer": ["Small organisms get trapped on viscous resins secreted by trees", "Leaves preserved as thin films of carbon", "Negative impressions of hard parts of organisms"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Match the bivalves in Group I with their modes of life in Group II:\n\nGroup I:\nP. Gryphaea\nQ. Mya\nR. Mytilus\nS. Pecten\n\nGroup II:\n1. Swimming\n2. Unattached, free-lying\n3. Burrowing\n4. Sessile byssate",
      "options": [
          "P-4, Q-1, R-2, S-3",
          "P-4, Q-3, R-2, S-1",
          "P-2, Q-3, R-4, S-1",
          "P-2, Q-1, R-4, S-3"
      ],
      "answer": "P-2, Q-3, R-4, S-1"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following changes occurred during the evolution of Equidae?",
        "options": [
            "Number of lateral digits or toes increases",
            "Decrease in hypsodonty",
            "lengthening of skull in front of the orbit",
            "Limb ratios remained constant"
        ],
        "answer": "lengthening of skull in front of the orbit"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following gastropods has/have siphonal canal?",
      "options": [
          "Cerithium",
          "Cypraea",
          "Fusus",
          "Murex"
      ],
      "answer": [ "Cerithium", "Cypraea", "Fusus", "Murex"]
    }
  ],
  "2020": [
    {
      "question": "Choose the correct pair(s): (Multiple Select Question)",
      "options": [
          "Proterozoic – Origin of flowering plants",
          "Paleozoic – Origin of amphibians",
          "Mesozoic – Acme of trilobites",
          "Cenozoic – Dominance of mammals"
      ],
      "answer": ["Paleozoic – Origin of amphibians", "Cenozoic – Dominance of mammals"]
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following pairs is NOT correctly matched?",
      "options": [
          "Productus - Brachiopoda",
          "Redlichia - Arthropoda",
          "Belemnites - Cephalopoda",
          "Gryphea - Gastropoda"
      ],
      "answer": "Gryphea - Gastropoda"
    }
  ],
  "2021": [],
  "2022": [],
  "2023": [],
  "2024": [],
  "2025": []
}
